A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Office Files of William O. Sweeney FA680
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Office Files of William O. Sweeney
1969-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA680
7.2 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access note
Material is open for scholarly research, with prior archival review.
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment. Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Ford Foundation
- Chronological Correspondence, 1970-1974; I
  - 1970-1971 WOS Chron File, Dec 1970-May 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1971 WOS Chron File, Jun-Dec 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 WOS Chron File (Box 1)
  - 1973 WOS Chron File (1/2), Jan-Jul 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1973 WOS Chron File (2/2), Jul-Dec 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 WOS Chron File (1/2), Jan-Jun 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1974 WOS Chron File (2/2), Jul-Dec 1974 (Box 1)
- Asian Communications Training Service (ACTS), 1977-1979; II
  - ACTS -- "Population Communication Consultants" Revision Prepared by Robert Griffin with William O. Sweeney, Dec 1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS -- for Population Reports and Mailings, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 1 -- To Do, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 1 -- General, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 1 -- Consultants, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 1 -- Washington Meeting, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 1 -- Hong Kong Meeting (October 1977), 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS Country Files, A-C, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ATS (ACTS) Country Files, I-V, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ATS (ACTS) Countries -- Reports, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 3 -- 1. Commercial -- CBD, Marketing, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 3 -- 2. Education -- Formal Population Education Paper, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 3 -- 3. East-West Communication Institute (EWCI) (AID review only), 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 3 -- 4. Information Services, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 3 -- 5. Journalism -- Development, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 3 -- 6. Public Relations, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 3 -- 7. Private Agencies, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 3 -- 8. Service Characteristics, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 4 -- 9. Technical Assistance, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 4 -- 10. Training Methodology, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 4 -- 11. Urban Programs and Family Planning Strategies, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 4 -- 12. Women, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 4 -- 13. Population and Integration of Development Topics, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 4 -- 14. Communications and Census Taking, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 4 -- 15. Training in Simple Research Methods, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 4 -- 16. Low-Cost Communications Technology, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 4 -- 17. Data Analysis, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- IV. Subjects, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- V. Sites, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- VI. Personnel, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- VII. Donors, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- AID, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- EWCI, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- IBRD (World Bank), 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- IDRC, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- IPPF, 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS 5 -- UNFPA, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS -- Final Report, Notes, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS -- Final Report -- Draft Two, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - ACTS -- Radel Back-up Materials, 1977 (Box 2)
  - "ACTS for Population - A Proposal", Nov 1977 (Box 2)
  - ACTS -- New Proposal, 1979 (Box 2)
- Subject Files, 1969-1980; III
  - Brazil, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - Centro Interamericano de Adeistramiento en Comunicaciones para Poblacion (CIACOP) -- Correspondence, 1974-1980 (Box 3)
  - CIACOP -- Papers, 1970-1980 (Box 3)
  - Costa Rica, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Colombia, 1975-1980 (Box 3)
  - El Salvador, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  - Guatemala, 1970-1974 (Box 3)
  - Guyana, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Health Education Conference -- West Africa, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Universidad Iberoamericano (1/2), 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - Universidad Iberoamericano (2/2), 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - Indonesia Visit, Nov 1978 (Box 3)
  - Institute of Child Health (ICH), 1978 (Box 3)
  - International Planned Parenthood Federation (IPPF) -- New York, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - Jamaica, 1970-1975 (Box 3)
  - Latin America, 1970-1980 (Box 3)
  - Mexico, 1976-1980 (Box 3)
  - Peru, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Philippines Visit, Nov 1978 (Box 3)
  - Trinidad (one letter), 1975 (Box 3)
  - United States -- Training Institutions -- Social Sciences -- Material from Field Visits, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
  - Women -- Outline Re: Ford Foundation Programs (Box 3)
  - Africa -- Economic Commission for Africa (ECA) -- Women's Centre, 1975-1978 (Box 4)
  - Africa -- Senegal -- Famille et Developpement -- Basic Documents, RGA, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Africa -- Senegal -- Famille et Developpement -- ASAFED, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
  - Africa -- Senegal -- Famille et Developpement -- World Neighbors, 1972-1979 (Box 4)
  - Africa -- Senegal -- Famille et Developpement -- Educational Programs, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Africa -- Senegal -- Famille et Developpement, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Famille et Developpement -- Report -- Back-up Materials, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Famille et Developpement -- Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Population Office Review -- Population Communications Memoranda, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- DAP Supplement, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- Expenditure and Project Breakdowns, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- Evaluation, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- Evaluation -- Miscellaneous Papers (1/2), 1969-1980 (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- Evaluation -- Miscellaneous Papers (2/2), 1969-1980 (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- Evaluation -- Interview Notes Re: Section VIII, The Future, [1980] (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- Evaluation -- Interview Notes, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- Ford Foundation Financial Reports, 1973-1980 (Box 4)
  - Population Communications Project (DAP 709-0024) -- RGAs, 1972-1979 (Box 4)
- Reports (Sweeney and Ford Foundation), Conference Papers, 1971-1980; IV
  - Conference Papers Re: Population and Family Planning (miscellaneous conferences), 1971-1974 (Box 5)
  - "An Inquiry into the Uses of Instructional Technology" Volume I by James W. Armsey and Norman C. Dahl, Mar 1972 (Box 5)
  - "An Inquiry into the Uses of Instructional Technology" Volume II, Appendices by James W. Armsey and Norman C. Dahl, Mar 1972 (Box 5)
  - Background Papers for Ford Foundation Meeting on Population (Elsinore, Denmark), Jun 1972 (Box 5)
  - Telecommunications Task Force #1 (materials from binder) (1/2), 1972-1973 (Box 5)
  - Telecommunications Task Force #1 (materials from binder) (2/2), 1972-1973 (Box 5)
  - "Communications and the Population Program of Pakistan" by William O. Sweeney, Aug 1973 (Revised Jun 1975) (Box 5)
  - "Population Communications in the Philippines" by William O. Sweeney, Jul 1974 (Box 5)
  - "A Report on the Activities of the Press Foundation of Asia" by William O. Sweeney, Jul 1974 (Box 5)
  - "An Examination of Communications Activities in the International Division for Fiscal Years 1973 and 1974" by the Office of Communications, Apr 1975 (Box 5)
  - "Report to the United Nations Fund for Population Activities on a Mission to Pakistan" by William O. Sweeney, Jun 1975 (Box 5)
  - "International Communications: Activities in the Developed and Developing Countries" by the Office of Communications, Jul 1975 (Box 5)
  - "Communications, Population, and Development in the Philippines" by William O. Sweeney, Aug 1975 (Box 5)
  - "Indonesia: Population Information and Education" by William O. Sweeney, Feb 1977 (Box 5)
  - "Ford Foundation Assistance in West and Central Africa", Oct 1977 (Box 5)
  - Memorandum -- "Population Office Communications DAP: Report of Activities" from Ann Leonard to Oscar Harkavy and William Sweeney, Sep 1, 1978 (Box 5)
  - "Egypt. A Preliminary Assessment of a Project Concerned with Population Information, Education and Communication" by Lyle Saunders, Douglas Larson and Wiliam Sweeney, Nov 1978 (Box 5)
  - "Population Communication Consultants" by Robert Griffin and William O. Sweeney, Dec 1978 (Box 5)
  - "Current Interest of the Ford Foundation", Jun 1980 (Box 5)
  - Sweeney Publications Re: Population, Family Planning, and Communications (1/2), 1973-1977 (Box 5)
  - Sweeney Publications Re: Population, Family Planning, and Communications (2/2), 1973-1977 (Box 5)
  - Glattbach, Jack -- Publications Re: Population Communications, 1975-1977 (Box 5)
- East-West Communication Institute -- Population Communication Documents, 1977; V
  Biographical / Historical
  The Center for Cultural and Technical Interchange between East and West, Inc. (East-West Center), was established in Honolulu, Hawaii by the United States Congress in 1960 to promote better relations and understanding among the nations and peoples of Asia, the Pacific area, and the United States.
  In June 1971 the East-West Center received a USAID grant of $1.072 million to enhance the Center’s ability to serve as an information, education and communications resource for population programs, primarily in the Asian and Pacific regions. In 1974 a second USAID grant of $1.6 million was awarded.
  In 1977, East-West Communication Institute (EWCI) of the East-West Center informed various institutions of the availability of the entire EWCI Population Communication Documents collection on microfiche, and 22 sets of microfiche were provided to developing country organizations, including the Ford Foundation.
  Scope and Contents
  The Population Communication Documents collection includes publications by William O. Sweeney.
  - East-West Communication Institute -- Catalog of Population Communication Documents, Jul 14, 1977; 1 Files Catalog; 2 Box(es) Microfiche documents. 4x6x12 inches. (Box 5)
  - East-West Communication Institute -- Population Communication Documents, A - O, 1977; Microfiche (Box 6)
    Arrangement
    Documents are arranged alphabetically by author's name.
  - East-West Communication Institute -- Population Communication Documents, P - Z, 1977; Microfiche (Box 7)
- Sweeney's Population Research Index, 1978; VI; 2 Box(es) 4x6x12 inches each.
  Sweeney’s population research index is arranged into three sections: SUBJECT, COUNTRY, and AUHTOR.
  “The SUBJECT index is broken down into a substantial number of items which are handled alphabetically. The pink cards which follow contain all of the bibliographic terms (subject headings).
  COUNTRY file is broken down by continent or area of the world and then by country.
  There are 3 kinds of materials in the system. Those with numbers beginning with 100; they are filed in drawers. The second have a letter and then a number. They are filed in loose-leaf notebooks and placed on the shelf of my office. Those marked “BK” and have a number are in books on shelves in my office and marked according to the number.”
  - Subject index (Box 8)
  - Country index (Box 8)
  - Author index (Box 9)
- Appendix A: Reports, 1972
  - Armsey, James W. and Norman C. Dahl; An Inquiry into the Uses of Instructional Technology (Vol. I), Mar 1972 (Report #019926)